John Sauter

Location: Nashua, New Hampshire, USA e-mail: <u>John_Sauter@systemeyescomputerstore.com</u>

Telephone: (603) 424-1188

Linkedin: https://www.linkedin.com/in/john-sauter-9580b2232/
Portfolio: https://johnsauter.github.io/UNH_Bootcamp-20-React_Portfolio/

GitHub: https://github.com/JohnSauter

Summary

Experienced computer programmer who understands the discipline necessary to build products that work, on time and within budget. Worked in many languages and environments, from stand-alone microcomputers to room-sided mainframes. As a Principal Software Engineer, developed software products for Digital Equipment Corporation, a world-class computer manufacturer. Obtained a certificate in full-stack coding from the University of New Hampshire, developing skills in JavaScript and its add-on modules for front-end and back-end Web development. Can communicate effectively with users having a range of experience, from absolute beginners to highly-educated engineers and doctors who can only express their needs in their own language.

Technical Skills

- Operating Systems: Stanford Time-Sharing System; IBM Fortran Monitor System; IBM OS/360 and successors; Burroughs
 B-5000 and B-5500 Master Control Program; DEC TOPS-10 and TOPS-20; DEC OpenVMS; Microsoft Windows 3.1, NT,
 2000, XP, 7, 10 and 11; GNU/Linux
- Languages: Javascript; C; Python; Algol-60; Fortran; Lisp; Basic; Bliss-32 and -16; assembly language for IBM System/360, DEC PDP-1, PDP-6/10 and PDP-11
- Computers: IBM 7090; IBM System/360 and successors; Burroughs B-5000/B-5500; DEC PDP-1, PDP-6/10 and PDP-11; Intel and AMD-based X86_64 desktop and laptop PCs; Arduino

Work Experience

Assistant Administrator for UPS in Londonderry, NH

April 2019 to February 2022

- Oversaw the hour-to-hour operation of the building, making sure parts flowed smoothly through the system, and handling special requests from customers.
- Developed documentation for the routine processes to maintain consistency in operational procedures and efficiency in training new assistant administrators.

IT Technician for UPS in Londonderry, NH and Chelmsford, MA June 2015 to April 2019

- Installed, maintained and diagnosed technical problems with computers, printers, and other equipment, thus ensuring day-to-day efficiency of operations could be maintained.
- Fixed problems in other locations remotely or by traveling there since not all buildings have resident technical support.
- Maintained an adequate supply of spares so that if a piece of equipment failed the defective item could be replaced quickly.

IT Technician for Kforce and Mōdis in New Hampshire, Massachusetts, May 2009 to June 2015 Maine and New York

- Replaced servers in Home Depot stores, keeping their servers up-to-date and consistent from store-to-store.
- Installed Hewlett-Packard printers in U.S. Postal Service facilities, Bank of America branch offices and Liberty Mutual offices, ensuring that each location has fast and reliable printing.
- Upgraded Liberty Mutual computers running Microsoft Windows XP so their computers would continue to receive security updates.
- Surveyed, installed, upgraded and removed computers at Liberty Mutual offices, Genesis Healthcare and Lahey Clinic so they could benefit from the speed and reliability of modern computers.
- Developed and piloted a process for converting all of Corning's personal computers to Microsoft Windows 7 so their computers would continue to receive security updates.
- Upgraded or replaced 3,000 computers at the Dartmouth-Hitchcock Medical Center in Lebanon, NH, working with a team, so
 that Dartmouth-Hitchcock would not be running an obsolete version of Microsoft Windows that would no longer receive
 security updates.
- Supported for declining to install a printer without help that required a four-man lift so that the installation could be completed safely the following week when Kforce assigned two technicians to the task.

Security Officer for Allied-Barton in Merrimack, NH

May 2012 to July 2013

- Automated a spreadsheet used by the Captain so he would not have to count the hours assigned to each Security Officer by hand.
- Guarded Merrimack Premium Outlets, a high-end shopping center, so customers would feel safe when shopping and the shop owners would not suffer vandalism.

Computer Operator for BAE Systems in Nashua, NH

December 2008 to March 2009

• Scheduled jobs using Tidal, making sure all user jobs ran when required.

Customer Support Specialist for GlobalCerts, LLC in Bedford, NH

May 2006 to May 2008

- Assisted customers to make good use of the SecureMail Gateway, making sure their e-mail was secure against unauthorized viewing or undetected corruption.
- Provided feedback to the development team from customers so they could develop the product in directions that would attract
 new customers.
- Found a workaround for a software compatibility issue that would otherwise have required recall of all SecureMail Gateway appliances.

Computer System Operator for the Town of Hudson in New Hampshire

November 1995 to February 2006

- Wrote and maintained local software so that our needs could be met precisely.
- Improved our local automobile registration software to handle the transition from 1999 to 2000 without needing to re-train the clerks. The software would do context-sensitive analysis to convert a two-digit year typed by a clerk to a four-digit year stored in the database. For example, a date of birth would always be in the past, whereas the expiration date of a just-issued automobile registration would always be in the future. In 1998, converting the database to four-digit years found a driver who had been born in 1899.
- Installed PCs, servers and printers so these would be available to Town staff for conducting Town business efficiently.
- Designed and maintained the computer network so that computer users could communicate quickly and reliably.
- Consulted on vendor software acquisitions to verify that they provided good value to the Town and would work with our existing software.

Business Owner of System Eyes Computer Store in Nashua, NH

July 1992 to December 1997

- Developed a spreadsheet to assess the fiscal health of the company, so we could confidently purchase products to sell.
- Sold and serviced the Commodore Amiga and the NewTek Video Toaster.
- Provided the Fred Fish library for the cost of media so Amiga users could choose freely from the library.
- Took classes in the Video Toaster to improve support for local Video Toaster users, making them more productive.

Senior and Principal Software Engineer for Digital Equipment Corporation in Massachusetts and New Hampshire

October 1975 to July 1992

- Designed and developed the DN60 communications processor, which let customers having both DEC and IBM mainframes communicate between them.
- Assisted in the development of DDCMP, an ancestor of Ethernet, by implementing the committee's resolutions and bringing
 performance data to the next meeting.
- Contributed to the VAX run-time library, which provided useful subroutines for VMS developers.
- Created the VAX BASIC run-time library so developers who prefer to code in BASIC can run their programs on VMS.
- Led the EDT version 3 project which provided a text editor for both PDP-11 and VAX users, thus making the transition from the PDP-11 to the VAX easier.
- Assisted in the development of DECforms, the successor to FMS, which provided a convenient way to structure a form-based user interface.

Scientific Programmer for Sanders Associates in Nashua, NH

November 1968 to October 1975

- Re-wrote the TOPS-10 magnetic tape device driver, making it easier to maintain and better able to deal with errors on a magnetic tape.
- Added an accounting exit to our OS/360 system so we could charge computer time to the company's cost centers.
- Developed the operating system for a telecommunications application installed in Michigan Bell offices in Detroit.
- Added disk pack drives to the PDP-10, using a device driver written by a third party.
- Developed software to cache the directories of DECtapes, so some DECtape operations did not require that the tape be mounted.
- Wrote software to match the TOPS-10 authorization file against the corporate personnel file, so terminated employees would quickly lose their access to the PDP-10.

System Programmer for Stanford University in Stanford, CA

June 1967 to November 1968

- Starting with the RCC 2.4L version of the PDP-6 monitor, added support for the Librascope disk drive to provide a high-speed alternative to using DECtapes for storing user data.
- Implemented a robust backup procedure which always placed my data at the front of the tape for maximum reliability.
- When the Artificial Intelligence project acquired a PDP-10 processor, updated the operating system so that user programs could use both the new and the old CPU, an early example of asymmetric multi-processing.
- Maintained and modified the PDP-6 monitor and TOPS-10 so researchers at the Stanford AI project could have the computer resources they needed on a time-sharing basis. The alternative would have been that each researcher would need to schedule exclusive use of the computer to do his work, which would have meant that much less research would be possible.

Education

Certificate in Full Stack Web Development from the University of New Hampshire, September 2022. This is a 24-week intensive program focused on technical programming skills in HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, JQuery, SQL, MongoDB, Heroku, Node.js and its many modules.

BS in Statistics from Stanford University, June 1967. Contributed to the Stanford Time-Sharing System, implemented the Case statement for the B-5500 Algol compiler, and wrote test software for Algol-W.